You may have a situation where you have to
print multiple rows of players, almost in
a tab or table format, and you want complete
control of the spacing within the print statement.
I will start another f-string on line 8, and
this time, I will print the player name and
score.
Then, I will add a colon, a less than symbol,
and 15 to the end of the player1 variable
to indicate that I want that variable to take
15 spaces and be left-aligned.
I will rerun the code, and the last print
statement formats the output as advertised.
If I want the score to take 10 spaces and
be right-aligned, what should I do here?
How about we try a colon, greater than symbol,
and 10 after the score variable.
I will run the code, which seems to work,
but to ensure it works, I will change the
name and the score, rerun the code, and look.
The spacing and alignment is consistent for
the values in these two outputs.
The last string format we are going to look
at is akin to the printf function seen in
other programming languages.
Python doesn’t have a defined printf function,
but, it can use a percent symbol along with
a number and letter combination to define
a specific format for text or a number.
I will type, on line 9, print, and then placeholders
for the Player1 and Score variables.
Then, after each colon, I will add the exact
format I want for each variable.
I will type %1s after the colon for player1
to indicate one space and a string.
After the colon following score, I will type
%.2f to indicate I want the score to show
with two numbers after a decimal point.
By the way, d indicates a whole number and
f indicates a floating-point decimal.
The question remains: how do we tell these
placeholders to match up to the player1 and
score variables?
After the text, I will add a %, which in this
context is known as the Modulo operator, and
then the order of the variables I want in
parentheses, those being player1 and score.
Let’s run this code and see the results.
The last line shows the formatted text as
we wanted in the print statement on line 9.